<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>GSoC'18 @ CERN</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2018-05-15T23:53:48+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Ravi Kiran S</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>GSoC'18 @ CERN-HSF</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/06/intro/"/>
   <updated>2018-05-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/06/intro</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Everyone, I am glad to inform that I have been selected as a &lt;strong&gt;Student Developer in Google Summer of Code 2018&lt;/strong&gt; at CERN-HSF. I am really excited to contribute to the project. I will be working on the project &lt;strong&gt;“Additional Machine Learning Project Ideas and Areas of Interest”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/GSOC18//images/gsoc18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GSoC'18&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CERN-HSF&lt;/strong&gt; (High-Energy Physics Software Foundation) is the umbrella organization for high-energy physics-related projects in GSoC. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://hepsoftwarefoundation.org/&quot;&gt;HEP Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt; facilitates the coordination of common international efforts in high-energy physics software and computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working on TMVA which is a submodule of ROOT Project ( One of the famous projects by CERN ). &lt;strong&gt;ROOT&lt;/strong&gt; is a modular scientific software framework. It provides all the functionalities needed to deal with big data processing, statistical analysis, visualisation and storage. It is mainly written in C++ but integrated with other languages such as Python and R. The &lt;strong&gt;Toolkit for Multivariate Data Analysis with ROOT (TMVA)&lt;/strong&gt; is a standalone project that provides a ROOT-integrated machine learning environment for the processing and parallel evaluation of sophisticated multivariate classification techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My project aims to implement the &lt;strong&gt;optimization modules&lt;/strong&gt; including “Gradient Descent with Momentum, RMSProp and Adam”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More Information about the project can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5779525665816576&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this summer will be interesting,challenging and productive. In my next post, I’ll give an overview of the optimization modules.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
